<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Jeremy&#39;s Ramblings</title>
    <link>https://jeremyceri.se/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Jeremy&#39;s Ramblings</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 22:14:21 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremyceri.se/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>RLDBAR Sidenote #1: Cameras</title>
      <link>https://jeremyceri.se/post/sidenote-1-cameras/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 22:14:21 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremyceri.se/post/sidenote-1-cameras/</guid>
      <description>This is the first of what I anticipate to be several sidenotes to the main RoguelikeDev Builds a Roguelike shenanigans. These sidenotes will deal with things that are not covered in the main tutorial, but I still feel add value, either to gameplay, programming knowledge, or both. For the inaugural Sidenote, we&amp;rsquo;ll be discussing adding a camera to our in progress roguelike. A camera will give us a couple of benefits, but the most immediate is that we can support maps larger than the terminal window.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RoguelikeDev Builds A Roguelike, Week 1, Part 2</title>
      <link>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-1-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 20:25:13 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-1-part-2/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back to my series following along with RoguelikeDev Builds a Roguelike! This is the second part of Week 1, the first being concerned with creating a player representation and moving it around using player input. In the second part of this week, we&amp;rsquo;re going to start thinking about the overall structure of our game, as well as get an intial version of the gameplay map, which is the world the player will be interacting with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RoguelikeDev Builds a Roguelike, Week 1, Part 1</title>
      <link>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-1-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2017 22:33:11 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-1-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to my series following along with RoguelikeDev Builds a Roguelike! This is Week 1, and this week, we&amp;rsquo;ve got things split into two parts. The first part, which this post will be concerned with, involves displaying the player and the screen, and implementing basic four direction movement. Part two will consist of creating a generic &amp;lsquo;Object&amp;rsquo; type that will represent things in the game, as well as creating an initial dungeon map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets dive right in creating our player, and getting it moving!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RoguelikeDev Builds a Roguelike, Week 0</title>
      <link>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 23:54:35 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremyceri.se/post/roguelike-dev-week-0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So it begins! This is the first in a series of posts following my attempts at making a Roguelike, in Go, using BearLibTerminal. I&amp;rsquo;ll be following along with the &lt;code&gt;RoguelikeDev builds a Roguelike&lt;/code&gt; posts as I progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, without further ado, lets begin week 0: Setup!`&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>