<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeremy Cerise </title>
    <link>http://jeremyceri.se/categories/colorado/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jeremy Cerise</author>
    <rights>(C) 2016</rights>
    <updated>2016-03-04 17:52:46 -0600 -0600</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>A brief history of Pittsburg, Colorado</title>
          <link>http://jeremyceri.se/post/brief-history-pittsburg-colorado/</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2016 17:52:46 -0600</pubDate>
          <author>Jeremy Cerise</author>
          <guid>http://jeremyceri.se/post/brief-history-pittsburg-colorado/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I took a short ski trip up to the ghost town of Pittsburg, and decided
the town had an interesting enough history to warrant a quick post about its
past.
&lt;!--break--&gt;
So, without further ado:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/zmNkahl.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is what Pittsburg looks today (with quite a bit of snow on the ground).
No buildings left, and certainly nothing resembling a town. Nothing much at all,
really, aside from some vacation homes (which are out of sight in this shot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, lets set the clock back about 120 years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/CZYeTc8.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so there&amp;rsquo;s still not much of a town, but certainly more than in my current
picture&amp;hellip; There&amp;rsquo;s a few house, and the most obvious building is the large mill
in the center of the picture, which would have been used for processing ore from
the various mines that supported the town (and its neighbor, Hidalgo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And really, the story of those mines is what makes it interesting. The major
player in the area was the Augusta mine, located a little ways away in
Poverty gulch. The Augusta mine was a decent producer, and stories mention that
it had a pay streak (vein of mineralization) of anywhere from 10 to 30 feet wide.
The primary production was silver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/ka3GwPn.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Augusta mine was well known for having an almost inaccessible route to the
mine itself. It was often said that burros were the only creatures who could
make the trip with ease. The area around it was also prone to avalanches, such
that the outbuildings were destroyed several times. One winter, in 1904, several
of the miners became fed up with the constant threat of avalanches, and decided
to make for Pittsburg, despite the warnings of the superintendent, and the newly
fallen snow. About a mile from the mine, an avalanche struck, killing six of the
party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, the Augusta was purchased by a Colonel Stanford, brother to the
founder of Stanford university, for $300,000. The colonel attempted to sell the
mine to a group of unsuspecting Englishmen for $3,000,000. Unfortunately, the
potential buyers were smarter, and had a mining engineer in the area. The
engineer travelled to the mine, in the dead of winter, and assessed the mine at
no more than $300,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mines around Pittsburg eventually failed (due in no small part to the costs
of transportation, the rugged terrain, and the silver crash of 1893), and
eventually the town was abandoned. Nothing of the original town remains today,
except the odd foundation and old road.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
